Good morning.
As everyone's getting settled, and I know none of you are unfamiliar, if you're
coming to speak to anything, please come to the table before you start speaking so
we can capture it on the Hansard.
And please don't be afraid of sitting on the end two
seats
of these sides.
Good morning, everybody. We're here to complete our hearing with
Immigration New Zealand in respect of the further information that we've
received to date.
Welcome. And to you, Nick,
or to your colleagues, we're happy to have introductory remarks.
If we could keep them to a limit of about two or three minutes, that would be
great. Over to you.
Thank you. Thank you, Madam Chair. And yes, I will talk quickly.
I have a few points to make. Thank you for the opportunity to be here today.
I do have with me Andy Milne, Deputy Secretary of Immigration New Zealand,
and Paul Stocks, Deputy Secretary for Corporate and Digital,
our Chief Financial Officer, Sharon Mitchell, and others that we'll call on during
the session. I want to start by acknowledging the significant events
since MBIE last appeared before you.
I do deeply regret the position that we find ourselves in, and I recognize that
we have a mountain to climb to rebuild the trust and confidence of this committee
and of Parliament and our public. As chief executive, I take
responsibility for the failures, and I'm taking accountability by
making the changes needed to strengthen the organization, and I know that I will be
judged on the results. I've made it clear within MBIE that our evidence before
all select committees must be accurate, complete, candid, and that senior
leaders are accountable for the quality of every appearance.
The serious and wide-ranging failures in the BCU project included
decision-making, oversight, reporting, governance, and vendor management.
And in the June hearing, I believe the expenditure that we provided was
the complete information. But shortly after, additional expenditure of
6.2 million was discovered and the record was corrected.
Now, I'd like to set out just some additional information on the project and the
related biometric projects that were shared with ministers and the committee this
week.
The audit office determined that the BCU was incorrectly capitalized in June
2025, and that will now be reversed in MBIE's accounts.
MBIE's now recommended to ministers to write off the capital portion of
in-person enrollment, the related biometric projects, because the
assets are now considered unusable.
We've also now reported to the committee the NEC settlement of 1.9
million and additional costs sitting outside the project of
549,000. Consequently, the total estimated cost for the two
projects is now 50.7 million, 42
million for the BCU,
and 8.7 million for IPE. That's in-person enrollment.
It's unacceptable that these two biometric projects have cost over $50
million and have not delivered. I do not yet have confidence that we have a full
and accurate picture of the project's costs, and this has raised fundamental
questions about the quality of the financial controls and investment oversight
within MBIE, and an independent financial review by KPMG is underway to
provide that full information. In response to these deeply concerning failures,
I've set up a structured program of assurance work.
Since we were last before you, we've now completed a stocktake of 70
active technology projects. Of these, 31 met the
threshold for formal governance, and we published this information on Monday.
The review found that MBIE has the frameworks, governance structures, controls, and
processes expected of a large public sector organization while
identifying areas to strengthen.
And at the time of the stocktake in July, nine projects were rated red and
six amber. And I've sought assurance that credible action is underway to address
the performance of these projects.
We've also completed a review of our wider investment and governance system, and a
12-month program to strengthen that is also underway.
Going forward, we will report publicly on a quarterly basis on our technology
portfolio so that there is open scrutiny on whether our changes are improving
performance. An active programme of work is also addressing
how concerns are raised, heard, and acted on, and that's focused on leadership,
integrity, and open communication.
I'll consider the Public Service Commission's hearing report findings and take any
necessary action, including employment actions where appropriate.
No options are ruled out. The underlying need to modernize Immigration New
Zealand's aging biometric capability remains.
Existing systems remain operational while work continues on that future approach.
The lessons from BCU continue to inform our approach to our future
services. Phase one has delivered significant elements of the program, but
assumptions in the business case relating to productivity and overhead savings were
too ambitious and cannot be achieved as originally forecast.
This project is not in the same position as BCU.
By the end of this calendar year, all the visa products envisaged in phase one
will have been delivered, and a deliberate checkpoint was built in to assess the
progress before moving to phase two.
However, full information about the red status of the project should've been
reported to ministers earlier, and in line with the changes to all major projects,
will now provide clear quarterly reporting to ministers that is subsequently made
publicly available.
We welcome the Public Service Commission's independent review into our future
services, and will use its findings to inform cabinet's decisions about the
program in the first quarter of 2027.
So it's appropriate today that we are here today to face further scrutiny.
We've learnt tough lessons, and we'll be rebuilding trust through transparency,
independent scrutiny, and sustained delivery.
I don't want our failings to diminish the contribution MV and its people make to
New Zealand every day. They deliver essential services , support
innovation and economic growth, provide policy advice to government, and steward
regulatory systems that New Zealanders and businesses rely on.
Their work deserves an organization with strong systems, sound governance, and a
culture in which concerns are raised and acted on.
Delivering that is my responsibility, and we welcome the committee's questions.
Thank you, Nick. And in light of what you've raised, I'm just going to start off.
When you split the project into its various
parts, did you tell the minister?
So it was--
Paul, let's go to the timeline.
It was split, and it was originally two projects back
in 2018 and '19. They were
then subsequently merged and then split again
in late 2023.
I would have to confirm whether or not the minister was advised at that point.
Now, all of these
things around did the right things happen with ministers are part of the hearing
inquiry. They will be looking into did the right things happen at the right
times.
Is there anything to add to that? I think it was just late '24 when it was
split back out again.
So sorry, are you answering that you did tell the minister when it was split back
out in '24?
No, I'm just correcting that it was December '24 according to my notes, where the
two projects were split again.
Okay. And sorry, and to answer my question, was the minister notified when
that happened?
I don't know. Would need to follow up on that one.
Okay, that would be good. And then to that point,
at that point when they were split, were you over the 35
million threshold
of cabinet approval?
I think the answer is no.
However, what I would say on this is
whole of life is meant to mean the whole of life, not just the point
up to which you've finished the build.
It should actually mean the usable life of the project as well.
I think it's quite clear that even though
they were getting close to the whole of life cost, actually that should've been
flagging issues much earlier because the life of
the actual deliverable project hadn't started yet.
So that's not the way we should be thinking about whole of life costs.
It should be thinking about the whole of life, and that's what
we are now doing with all of our projects to make sure they are properly
accounting for whole of life costs. So that's the going forward.
I believe that at the time it was under the 35 million, but as I
say, whether that was...
And clearly now it's gone over 35 million.
Yeah. And just to ask, you've mentioned that the IPE is
unusable without the software. So can I ask why they were separate in the first
place?
Well,
I think in part that's a question for the hearing inquiry, but
they were separate and then together.
So the two products do quite different things.
The BCU provides the core biometric
database, if you will. In-person enrollment was actually a product which
was to do two things. Firstly,
when you take biometrics, whether it's fingerprints or
photographs, generally you need some kit to do it.
The Immigration New Zealand had kit that was basically 23 kilos of
equipment.
Mm.
The in-person enrollment project was designed to have basically
a seven-kilogram suitcase that you could do in the field biometric enrollment,
for example,
if you were doing refugee assessments,
and the software associated with that.
So they're actually quite different, in terms of the products.
They're related because they both are biometrics.
The question about why they were joined is one that the hearing inquiry will
investigate. I can see why they were separated, because they are different things.
And we of course now need to still replace these
old systems.
Yeah.
And at this stage, I think we're still looking at them as two separate pieces of
technologies that we will need to roll out.
Okay.
I just really want to get to the bottom of that.
So,
what you're saying is that without the software,
this particular software, that kit is unusable.
So to me, that's a package.
The software, in in-person enrollment it was both the hardware and the software.
The software to allow the hardware to talk-
Mm
... to the rest of the system. So without that software-
... or some other software, that hardware is not
usable.
And there's been no consideration for holding onto it for potential future
software?
We have kept the hardware.
Okay.
But it's now three years into the life since we've owned it.
Yeah.
By the time that we actually get software to make it work, it might be five.
So the
book value of that may well be zero, even if we can still use it.
Okay. I have a supplementary question from Carl.
Thanks very much.
On to the next primary.
Chair, you talked about the point at which it was split.
If it was 34.9 for the project,
and then the BCU was eight million at the time it was split, wasn't
it, at that point, over the whole of life
cost?
I don't know if I've got that particular number.
Have you got that, Sharon?
Well-
At the time
... okay. So maybe the follow-up question to that is, at
any point during this project, was the project
genuinely within the whole of life cost
approval at the point in the project?
So take any point since 2019, was it genuinely
within the whole of life cost
at that point? And if so, can you tell me which point?
Sharon, can you answer that?
Approved by-
So at the point where the project was split, so in,
from FY20 through '24, we were sitting at
spend of underneath 35 million. So the two separate
projects were sitting at
30 million spend at about that point in time.
The challenge that we have, and Nick alluded to earlier, is that this
is project spend as opposed to what should be considered as whole
of life cost, which is the life of then having the project going forward.
So
then was it genuinely within whole of life cost?
You can't say,
well, the cost of the project was under the number, but
actually whole of life cost wasn't thought about.
So genuinely, was it within whole of life cost?
This is the-
Approvals
... core part of what the hearing inquiry is looking at with the allegations
around creative accounting, and whether or not the right
accounting practices were applied to these projects at
those points in time.
So at the point that the minister first
challenged the request for an increase in the whole of life cost,
which I understand happened in March
2024-
Mm-hmm
... was the changes around the accounting
a way of avoiding
further scrutiny by Cabinet or by the minister around the whole
of life cost, in your view?
So this is something for the hearing inquiry.
I do think at least one factor in their minds at the time was to
keep the projects under $35 million.
So Carl, did you have your primary still then?
Yeah, I'll come back to that.
Well, you're next.
Oh, right.
So if you could go onto it and then we'll come talk about it.
So
the capitalization of the project as a minimum viable product and the
creation of the BCU value stream, I
suppose that's what I've just asked you, was around the,
that was just another way of avoiding breaching the whole of life cost from all
that I can read.
So it's hard for me to go into intentions, but clearly,
they capitalized that too soon. That's what audit has determined.
We agree with that finding, and in my mind,
that value stream is part of the whole of life costs of the project.
Okay. So appreciate there's some inquiry work to be done around that, and you've
talked a lot about changes in process.
What I haven't read in the questions, 90 onwards, and what
you've said, is what's changed
in the culture of your organization to give us trust
and confidence that people are not trying to avoid ministerial
scrutiny or our select committee scrutiny in the future?
Yeah. And I will start this with the processes briefly, because the
processes are there to
make things visible and to make sure that people are following what they should be.
So I don't want to underplay those.
They are part of making sure that we are following our processes, is actually part
of ensuring that people are doing the right thing.
In addition, we have quite a lot underway on culture, and
that is around expectations of senior leaders about
a culture of integrity. It is about making it clear to the
organization that they should feel safe to speak up.
We made it easier to access the integrity line on our
homepage with our intranet after June.
And that has seen a jump up in people using that integrity line.
That's a good thing. People are raising things, and those things are being
investigated.
We currently have our
annual culture survey that's currently underway.
We put some specific questions in there about do people feel safe to speak
up, and we'll be looking at those results closely, and we were able to break that
down across the organization.
At the same time, the most recent public service census on the question
of do you feel safe to speak up showed that MBIE as a whole
actually was above the public sector average.
So I'm not sure we have something that is an endemic issue.
I think that there was clearly failings in this project, but from the
tech stocktake, that shows we don't have the same issues at all across the
other projects we need to strengthen.
And the same with those cultures. So we are doing a lot on culture, but
there are reasons to think that this is not something that is systemic across the
organization.
So we have a supplementary from Panji, and then we'll move on to the primary from
Raquel.
Thank you. In your opening remarks in regard to
this issue of restoring confidence, you mentioned independent
scrutiny, but independent scrutiny is as good as the information that is
available to that scrutiny, right?
Correct.
So what does that mean? Because it may not mean anything.
Well, if we go to the technology project, I don't know whether you want to talk
about what we have put online, because that is more than we have put
on before on projects, and we can continue to improve
that, but-
Thanks. So on Monday, we published a stock take of all of our
70 in-flight initiatives in the IT space.
Thirty-one of those were what we call major projects, and a major project is
anything over $250,000 of operating
costs or any capital investment at all.
And so what we've done is basically published all of our material on that.
We've had it independently verified by Maven Consulting as well.
We had our internal assurance teams
do the assessment of the state of the IT projects, both the state of
their finances, their deliverables, their benefits, where they were
on schedule, and the state of the reporting and governance around that
to make sure that we had the right tools and systems in place.
What we did find was, we didn't find any surprises about things
we didn't already know about. Which was reassuring, because we didn't know
about BCU.
And so we didn't find anything of that
nature. We have some IT projects, as you would expect,
with their red status, either because we think that we've got problems with the
benefits realization, they're behind schedule, or they're costing more.
And the trick about having a red status is it allows you as
governors, as the ministry, as ministers, as select committees, to
see what's going on, and it requires us to take some action on it.
So I'd be, for example, quite surprised if we didn't have major IT projects that
weren't either amber, which means there are some issues, or red, which means you
need to take action to resolve those.
We'll be publishing that stock take every quarter,
and they'll be available for review.
And that will also include where there have been significant IQAs, gateways,
that this committee rightfully raised that around BCU, why the IQAs hadn't been
published. On Monday for the future services, we've published all of
the IQAs and gateways, and that will now be part of the regular rhythm that we do
with the quarterly releases.
Mm-hmm.
All right.
We'll go to Riccardo's primary, and then we've got your primary next, Pam Shepherd.
So Riccardo.
Let's go to that. Can I take a step back?
And I'd like you to explain, because I think for people listening, they will just
be hearing acronyms. The BCU isn't just some change of
interface, right?
It's a project that would've dealt with people's biometric information.
Correct.
Would you be able to outline,
first of all, were there any commitments that were being followed
through as part of trying to do the BCU?
And
whose biometric information was this project supposed to capture to begin
with?
Yeah. I might get Amy to talk to that.
So there's a couple of components to when we talk about biometrics.
Paul's already talked about the in-person enrollment, IPE.
So that's the hardware-
Yeah
... and software that collects biometric details from a small
cohort of individuals that Immigration New Zealand deals with.
And that's largely people involved in our quota refugee program,
asylum claimants within New Zealand, any cases that
our investigations or fraud cases might be investigating,
and then anything that happens at the border, but just in relation to a very small
cohort of people where we have concerns around their identity or we may be looking
to turn them around upon arrival in New Zealand.
And unlike other jurisdictions, as you know, we don't collect mass biometric
data from individuals at the border.
And I'd also just like to point out this point, that people when they hear
biometrics at the border will think smart gates.
Those smart gates are not in our Immigration New Zealand system.
They're a custom system. And when we talk about BCU and IPE, we're not talking
about any of that smart gate technology at the border.
The core, so in terms of the BCU project, was
looking to replace the core of the biometric system.
And what that core does is it compares biometric details submitted
largely in relation to visa applications.
So when people submit a visa application, they submit a passport document and
a current photo, and the core matches those records and
gives us assurance that the people arriving in New Zealand are the people who they
say they are, and they have the correct identification.
So, that is the core that we need to replace still.
So the need to replace that still exists, and that's a piece of work that we'll be
looking at in the future.
And it's around verifying the identity of people that are applying for
visas to enter New Zealand.
And this was part of automating that information sharing with our
Migration Five countries partners, right?
So can I ask, by the time we had
the hearing where this exchange would have happened,
had security issues and cybersecurity issues been
identified?
And were there any sort of cybersecurity issues or security issues
within this project,
or risks that were identified as part of it that led to concerns?
Look, certainly clear there are no cybersecurity or security issues relating to our
current systems.
The upgrade, I meant.
In relation to the work that we were doing to replace not just the core but
the workflow, one of the things I understand that led to some complications with
the project was getting through the necessary security
stages for that to be operationalized, and it had never reached that point for
operationalization.
Were you aware of any security issues or cybersecurity issues that the company in
question had faced with any other
contracts or
capability upgrades that they were doing when you first purchased the equipment?
No, not that I'm aware of. No.
What is your knowledge of the types of
contracts that the company in question would have had?
Were you aware of the sort of work that it did before you went into it with it?
We know that
NEC, the company that
provide that core, are one of the leading providers in the world of
biometric systems.
And finally, what is the goal
of automated information sharing that you were trying to achieve with this project
with the likes of the United States for the likes of asylum seekers and refugees?
So what benefit
does this bring to us? And what safeguards were you hoping to have
for people who were, say, fleeing prosecution when it came to automating
that information sharing with the United States specifically?
So I think it's important to note that that is already automated
So there's already automated exchange of
fingerprint information between us and the migration five
countries, so the Five Eyes countries.
This project was looking to replace the core,
because it's old and it needs to be replaced.
And it's got
ongoing support at the moment, but it's on a best endeavors basis.
And the BCU project really got into difficulty because it
started looking at workflow elements of how the core integrates with
different parts of the immigration visa processing system.
So in the future, our priority is to replace the core, because that will give
us efficiency benefits around the automation that already happens.
And also to replace the equipment, the hardware and software that allows us
to capture fingerprints for that small cohort of people that we take biometric
data from. So they're the two aspects of the project which are going
forward, which are critical and need to be focused on immediately.
Where we brought the workflow
into play
through the BCU project, ultimately led to the challenges in the project
because that wasn't a specialism of the company that we were dealing with.
So that's where some of the-
And just finally, you did mention that
as part of the BCU project, there were some security issues that had been
identified.
When did you communicate those to the minister?
Because those are quite risky, right?
If you're going to be sharing biometric information through the use of
BCU, this is quite sensitive information.
I said-
When did you first hear that the minister that there were issues with security?
I don't know what was told.
Perhaps if I can help with this. There were issues associated with
cybersecurity around the BCU upgrade.
Those issues were not around external access, so our MB firewalls are
quite strong and we were confident in that.
There were questions around the certification and accreditation of the product
itself. And until products have gone through CNA, we're uncomfortable with
them having access to our internal system.
So the response to that was build what we called a walled garden
around the BCU, so it had very limited access to the rest of the MB systems.
As it never went into production, that was never turned on.
But those were the concerns that we were thinking about in cybersecurity.
Just finally, for the layperson, what are the
risks
of not having had those cybersecurity risks
addressed? What would have happened?
Well, the concern there was really about whether there was any risk to the rest of
the MB systems if this had not passed accreditation.
So we would not have turned it on with access to other MB systems.
Which is why we call it a walled garden, which basically says the
application is only allowed
certain access for the purposes it's required for, and it can't access the rest of
the system.
You never got to-
All right. We're moving-
Mr. Umbers
... We're moving on now.
You can't say "finally" three times.
Pam J, and then we need to get to Camilla.
Yeah. Thank you. About the staff who raised concerns about
BCU, who were sidelined, have you gone back and looked at when were those
concerns first raised, like how many years ago or how many months ago?
So that is absolutely part of the hearing inquiry into looking into those.
So,
we did do a check of were there any formal flags in the system, and my
understanding is there were no formal flags in the system.
But, the Greg James report does talk about this.
So that will be part of the hearing inquiry.
What I have focused on is how do we make sure that we are
having channels that people can raise things.
And as I said earlier, we've made that more visible.
People are raising things. That's a good thing.
In our current culture survey, we'll take the temperature of the organization to
see how people are feeling overall as well, and we'll look if there are any areas
that need particular focus, and we will do that across the organization.
So are you doing a proper investigation into who was actually sidelining these
people? Because the things that you're saying, they sound very general, because
every organization would say that.
But what does that mean at individual, somebody's behavior is like that,
which is basically obstructing
the information that needs to be passed on to be passed on, or punishing people,
those who are raising actually genuine concerns.
So on the past,
that is the focus or the topic of the hearing inquiry.
So we're not duplicating what that inquiry is doing.
For now,
when people are raising things through our integrity line, each one of those is
investigated through our integrity team.
Okay.
So they are taken seriously.
They will have conversations with the person who's raised the issue and then work
out what action to take as a consequence.
So every one of those that comes through our integrity line is taken seriously
and dealt with.
Okay, thanks.
We have a supplementary from Priyanka. Go ahead, Priyanka.
Thanks. Just on that, I take your point that the
retrospective factors contributing to this, whether cultural or
systemic, are part of the terms of reference for the hearing
inquiry. But clearly, you're not waiting for that to improve your system.
Correct.
You've mentioned that.
But
I agree
that what you've shared with us in terms of your improvements going
forward are very vague. Can you give us some clarity
around what you're changing?
If there was a culture where people didn't feel that they
could speak up and you've now formalized some structures, can you
share what those formalized avenues are?
And if there's a system of fear, is there a way for people to provide
information anonymously?
Yeah. So let me do a few of these specifics.
So, yes, they can absolutely do it anonymously.
One of the key channels is this integrity line, speak up line, and you can do that
through a form anonymously. You can ring an external provider and
provide that anonymously as well.
So, yes, absolutely, you can do that.
As I said, the culture survey, I do think that's an important part of what we are
doing because that gives us the evidence base.
That goes down to a branch level, a team level, so you can actually see where you
might have localized issues that are able to then be considered
specifically.
We've also been getting our senior leadership team out into our
sites across the country. It's the first time we've done that together
as a leadership team since before COVID.
And that's to show that we are there to have those quiet
conversations over a cup of tea as well.
People have appreciated the fact that we have been getting out around the country,
and that also shows visibility and makes people more comfortable raising things.
A lot of these are ultimately about leadership
and culture, and how do we make people feel that they are able to raise
things.
Yes. So what of that is new?
Well,
making the integrity line more visible is new.
Putting specific questions into our culture survey this year around speaking
up is new. Getting around the country as a senior
leadership team, that's new since before COVID.
We've put an additional expectations on all people leaders
around creating a culture of integrity.
That's been new this year as well.
There are a number of things that we have been putting in place, and there'll be
more to come.
But part of it is the senior leadership team, though.
So have you had any changes there, or have you had any
complaints around the senior leadership team not listening to
people who raise complaints?
So the senior leadership team, first of all, is actually quite new.
I
think I've appointed five people to the senior leadership team
this year, so there's been quite a lot of change in the senior leadership team.
I do see that as an opportunity that the organization is seeing a
new team forming that allows us to reset some of the functions.
Obviously, immigration is a large part of the organization, and he's been spending
a lot of time
out with people and listening, and bringing
ideas back.
So I agree, it starts with the senior leadership team, and
we've got a particular focus on culture
because culture does start with us.
Okay, we have a supplementary from Carl Bates.
Thanks, Chair. In terms of MB's processes around
capitalizing projects, were your team
following those when BCU was capitalized?
And if they weren't, what have you changed in terms of what
Priyanka was asking to ensure that they do in the future?
Yeah, thank you. Sharon will give you the thoughts of this.
So as far as our capitalization policy goes,
and also the accounting standard relating to capitalization of
intangibles.
The process was followed. However, the standard allows
for judgment
as to when is the right time to capitalize.
And in the standard, it specifically calls out that there is
judgment that does need to be applied, that you would be expected to get
support from both internal sources and external sources to
corroborate that the piece of kit that you're building is ready
to go.
I think in this case, there was undue reliance placed
on internal sources of evidence and insufficient
external corroboration of, is the system ready to go?
So would that explain why Audit New Zealand is saying that it shouldn't have been
capitalized and asking for it to be reversed, regardless of the fact that the
project is-
Yep
... no longer viable?
And it's my view as well. I think we were capitalizing it too early.
As Paul said, the system was not live, and so
you would typically expect a system to be live before you capitalized it.
And I should note, Sharon just started in January this
year. We do have quite a lot of work to do in our financial controls, and that is
Sharon's task to be bolstering that across a number of areas.
Which is a people issue, ultimately, right?
It's a people issue. It's a process issue.
It's a following and monitoring of controls issue.
It is a standards that are expected issue.
So all of those aspects are getting wound into a
financial capability uplift program that I'm leading across all
of MB to make sure that those standards, controls, and expectations
are clear and understood.
Grant, was that on the- This is on- Yeah ... this one. Yeah.
It's interesting.
Looking through the
timelines of the values
of the project as it
moved through, there's been various opportunities, various times where
they've gone to various ministers of the
day for their
continued support of the project, right?
To ratify, to allow, to
support the project.
So
one of those times, if I look back in November '21,
when you were looking to increase the scope of the project
at the time, and you had the immigration minister today, Kris
Faafoi, minister of finance,
Grant Robertson signed it off. And also the associate minister of the day, I think
Pike was included in the loop. Would
it be
reasonable to expect them to actually, at those points in time,
to
question you about
the project and where it was going?
I think there were
questions at different points in time.
And as the Greg James review found,
there were plenty of opportunities to stop this or do
things differently earlier, and they should've
been taken. There were a number of points, particularly in that 2023
period,
after it was paused.
So at what point did things finally come to a head?
Because obviously there's been opportunities in the past
at ministerial level. At what point do things finally come to a head where actually
the game's up and we've got to deliver on this?
We've got to fess up
So it was late 2025.
Yeah.
We had
an acting chief executive, Suzanne Stu, who came in with fresh
eyes,
and the overall judgment was this is not going to get there.
Yeah.
And that we need to-
And the current minister
give you that feedback as well, saying, "What's going on here?"
Absolutely. Yeah. The current minister was,
right from when we reported to her,
getting regular updates on this because she was concerned about it.
And so we advised those ministers, and then ownership minister
as well, in November, December of 2025, and they were
supportive of the plan to stop the project.
So you had a supplementary-
Yeah
... then we need to move on.
Sorry, Chair. Just in terms of what you've just said about it being challenged and
questioned through the process. My understanding is it was
joint ministerial approved November '21, increased to
30.4. September 2022, it went up to
31.9 without ministerial approval.
July 2023, it went up to 35 million with
ministerial approval. And it wasn't until, you said, late 2025.
It wasn't until March 2024 under the current Minister of
Immigration, where, in your words, it says,
"Challenged advice provided on project
starts and rising costs." And so I'm just
not sure that characterization that had been challenged throughout.
No, I didn't say that.
Okay.
I didn't mean to say that.
I said there were lots of opportunities where the project could've been done
differently.
Okay.
That's what the Greg James review found.
I think what he also found is that not nearly enough went to
ministers during the project.
Okay, so we have a supplementary from
So to clarify that then, when you say that there were ample opportunities
for things to be different, was it the passage of time and the fact
that it was a new project in 2021, and as time passed
and costs ballooned, and advice was, what, then
provided at some point to ministers?
Would it be fair to say that it came to a head because of a combination of
that? I'm assuming
ministers wouldn't challenge a project at the start of it.
That's right. Although, as I just said,
the review found there weren't enough flags going to
ministers
during the project. There were challenges.
In 2023, the Minister of Immigration at the time
declined to increase the whole of life cost above 35
million, for example,
related to concerns about the project.
So yeah, there were concerns at that
time. But as I said, what Greg James's review found was
that actually the project should've been stopped much earlier.
We need to move on to our next primary question, which is Camilla Belich.
Thank you. I just want to look forward, so not necessarily
the subject matter that's been covered by different reviews.
In the response that
the ministry has given to our written question 94,
talked about the steps that will be taken moving forward in terms of
preparation for select committees.
Yes.
And one of the steps that is listed is
making sure that relevant ministers' officers are fully briefed in
advance and not surprised by any statements made in the select committee or
hearing. Do you think there's an inherent issue
with
putting yourselves as officials or similar people
in your place when you have that type of expectation?
So if you can't say anything that
won't surprise the minister, or if you have to, according to your guidance,
make sure that the minister is aware of everything that comes up, does that prevent
you from being free and frank when you come to select committees?
And looking forward,
as this is something that you've said will be the process in the future.
That is part of how
the authority of officials to appear before select committee comes through the
minister, so that is
just
standard constitutional process.
But it doesn't prevent us from being clear and
candid with you.
The training that we are now
putting in place, all of the people
here have been through new training that we've put in place.
We've been developing new policy in line with the Public Service Commission's
updated guidance. So we're putting all of that in place.
That doesn't stop us at all. We have learnt our lessons, and we're changing our
approach to make sure that you're getting the full information.
Just
one supplement. So I suppose that, yeah, I understand that you-
One at a time
... so there's an inherent conflict, I suppose, in the sense that you work to the
government of the day, the minister of the day.
You've also got a no surprises policy, but you also need to be accountable
and fulsome and truthful to this committee.
Yes.
So in a situation in the future where,
for whatever reason,
you're not able to be as fulsome-
Yes
... as the committee would expect, how are you going to approach that?
Are you going to flag to the committee that
that's something that you can't discuss because of
some reason? I think there's an inherent conflict there, and I think that
probably does result in, not just in this example, but in
other officials and other select committees
not providing us with the information we need to properly scrutinize what's
happening in government.
Yeah. As you say, the correct thing to do is to say, well, this
information is currently, whether it's budget sensitive or
with ministers for decisions, and that's why we can't provide that
at this time. And then, depending on what it is, is that something
that we would need specific clearance from the minister to be able to provide or to
go into a secret session? That was part of the privileges committee
conversation, that
if we're not able to share something We need to say that we're not able to share
that
And that's your expectation moving forward for-
Absolutely
... for everyone at MB.
Absolutely.
I just wanted to ask around the white label
option and the decision to customize.
At what point in the project did you decide to
customize the potentially white label solution?
This is for BCU.
For BCU, yeah.
Do you know,
Andy?
I don't know the specific date. I think one of the challenges-
How many years or months into, roughly?
I think it was, in just
my
understanding of it, in the order of 2020.
And I think the issue was not just the customization, although that's always a
problem when we don't take off-the-shelf things.
But the project moved from what was an upgrade of existing
software to replacement. And at that point, it's a fundamentally
different proposition. And I think it wasn't just the customization.
You can customize an upgrade. It was moving from upgrading and
making sure your system was up to date, to building a new
system. And in my view, that was one of the problems.
And was that necessary?
I'm not in a position to make that judgment,
because I wasn't involved in it. I think it was that, though, that changed the
nature of the product.
Mm.
But what I'll also say is, when we think about what we're doing going forward and
looking at options, because we still need to find a replacement for these systems,
we're looking very hard at the all of government option, which is
Facial Recognition as a Service. So, we are very mindful
that as soon as you go down customization, different routes, you add in complexity
and risk. So we're looking hard at those other options.
Yeah. To my point was going to be that my limited experience with technology
projects, every time you try to customize, the cost will blow out.
Can I ask then, what would it cost if you went for a white
label project now?
Sorry. Andy?
We're anticipating that to replace the core that
I mentioned before will be
in the region of
the Cabinet threshold for approval.
So we've got ongoing costs associated with running our existing system,
approximately $7 million a year.
We will factor ongoing costs into that.
So to Sharon's point around how we calculate whole of life cost, but if you
calculate the whole of life cost to replace the core of the biometric system
with the new core, plus the work to do that, plus the ongoing life costs, it's my
expectation that that will reach the threshold.
And it's certainly something we would take for Cabinet approval.
And can you please confirm for those listening what the threshold is?
Thirty-five.
Right. And it would be under that?
No, I would imagine it will be in the... The team are working through exactly...
So we've reset the project.
At the moment, we're working to establish a new business case for investment.
But my anticipation, we've submitted a risk profile assessment to Treasury, which
is part of that process, and that suggests the cost would be in the region of that
Cabinet threshold-
Okay
... for investment.
That is when you take into account the whole life of the-
Yes
... including the annual running costs.
Yes. And I think we've got a bit of discrepancy around what is the
sort of cost in the whole of life.
Or the spend, sorry, and the whole of life cost.
Can I then ask, just in terms of the decisions around going from a white label
to a sort of boutique or customized solution,
you said that you have now a risk register.
Do you have an
element of your risk register that isn't just, it is over this amount
of money, but a relative proportion that now
goes beyond the original allocation?
So we've completely retooled the way in which we do our investment
decisions. And the first stage is what we call an investment light
map, which basically says, what is the problem you're trying to fix, what is the
solution, what do you think the cost is going to be, before you can even go to
develop a business case. And then after that, we're putting in place thresholds
that says it's not just the fiscal costs, it's the level of complexity
of the project, it's how many interactions it has with the rest of the ministry
systems. And certainly one of the things that would raise a risk flag is,
are you doing something unique, novel, different?
What makes this different from every other user that has similar systems?
And has anyone asked you that question along the process
in terms of auditing or ministerial intervention?
This is the question that our own governance boards ask whenever we're presented
now with new investment opportunities.
Why would you do something different from everyone else?
And we do still have the legacy of the past.
So if we think about future services, which is moving to our
new modern platform. But that new platform does have a lot
of what's called technical debt, which is where when that
was put in place in 2022,
it was done quite quickly, and that did cut some corners using
customizations. That's been one of the reasons that it's been
harder to put new things onto the platform now.
And so that's part of the logic for pausing migrations of new products,
and doing optimization on the platform itself to try and make that a more
usable and efficient platform.
We have a question from Ricardo.
How robust are your procurement processes when any C
corporation has had a history of procurement overcharging,
accounting irregularities, and IT security vulnerabilities that
span over several decades? All which I think are
related to, A, the cost of this project, security
issues that you've outlined, and from what documents we've seen,
issues that were not just within MB, but within the relationship
with NEC as well. Are you confident that the processes that you're using
on projects so sensitive that relate to people's biometric
information are robust enough when this company that you basically
engage with
had actually a history of overcharging and accounting issues?
So
what happened in this project back in 2020, and I'm not going to
defend the specific
procurement process then, but in terms of going forward, we follow the
government procurement rules, which another part of MBIE works on.
Paul, you might want to comment on how we're looking at our IT procurement.
But just-- Sorry, because you told me earlier that you were not aware of any sort
of issues that the company had faced on security, et cetera.
Even a cursory Google glance
shows a range of issues spanning a few decades.
Were you aware of those issues when you were embarking on the project or when, for
example, you were talking to the minister about what had occurred?
The original procurement was done back in 2020, and so none of us--
I'm not aware of what the conversations were at that time.
But go back to NEC's core matching technology, is
considered one of the world leaders, and it's at the heart of-
World biggest.
Yeah.
It's still used today in our system.
It's still used in DIA as well. The issue with the VCU
project was the workflow that went around the core matching
technology.
Thank you. A final question from Vanessa Wang.
So,
the average person over their entire working life in New
Zealand will pay roughly a million dollars, just under a
million dollars, that's one estimate, in tax.
So this project has spent the entire working
contribution of 50 people's
tax, and we have nothing to show for it.
How would you feel being in a room full of people
whose entire tax contribution had been essentially
wasted?
Well, it's unacceptable that-
Because you are in a room full of people who represent
those people, and I,
through all of this, have had the impression that
actually, the respect that's been given to the people of New
Zealand,
represented by us, has
been trodden all over. And MB has had a
culture of managing how ministers, in
particular, respond,
how you interact with this committee.
What's going to change in the future about the culture in MB and
possibly other public services about the people of New Zealand
and their representatives?
It's unacceptable
that these two projects have spent so much and have not delivered.
I absolutely agree with that. We take that really seriously.
That is why we're putting in place all these changes around how we govern,
how we manage large projects, how we make that information publicly available.
Sunlight is the best disinfectant. We haven't been transparent enough.
We're going to be more transparent.
We are also looking at those culture that if there are people that have
concerns, I want to make sure that they feel able to speak up, and that's why the
culture is just as important as the process changes.
We take these really seriously, but I hope you can see from today that
we are making changes. We are being more transparent.
We are making changes to our process to make sure that we are a much stronger
organization in future.
Right. Thank you. That's the end of our time.
We appreciate you making yourselves available.
We'll move into private session.
Thank you.
Just for a minute, team.